[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software your AI coding assistant has
loose lips it's constantly spilling your
data API Keys Cloud credentials and more
to llms as context stop leaks with code
gate it's a single lightweight container
you deploy to your desktop it sits
between your AI assistant and llm to
redact secrets and prompts and review
llm recommendations for bad dependencies
codegate is open source learn more at
COD gate. a that's Cod g a.
a welcome to se radio I'm bries am manut
and today our guest is Tanya Janka Tanya
is the author of Alice and Bob learn
secure coding Alice and Bob learn
application security and cards against
absc over her 28e it career she has won
multiple Awards including OAS lifetime
distinguished member and hacker of the
Year award and is a prolific blogger T
has trained thousands of software
developers and it Security Professionals
via her online academies V hack purple
and srep Academy and her live training
programs today we we going to talk about
how to integrate secure coding into
software development life cycle we have
covered secure coding Concepts in
episode 475 568 541 and 514 let's get
started with fundamentals Tanya what are
some fundamental security Concepts that
you feel every developer should know I
really want everyone to know about the
idea of least privilege the idea that we
only Grant exactly what a user or a
person needs so they only have access or
permissions or they can only see or do
the things they actually need to instead
of just opening the door all the way
when we don't need to another concept
that I think is really important is
usable security making sure when we
design secure Concepts that they're not
terrible for the end user because users
are really smart and tricky and they
will get around them and so if we make
our security features more pleasurable
to experience it's a lot more likely
that users will do what we want and make
the secure choices I could go
on I'm wondering how deep you want to go
on this question we dig deeper into each
of these principles or the concepts that
you mentioned as we go through the
podcast for the immediate next question
I wanted to ask you about trust and why
it's critical to stop assuming trust in
systems and data yes
so usually what I do is I explain the
concept of implied trust so users human
beings actually in general We Trust
we're very trusting compared to other
animals so if you look at Panthers if
they see each other they usually they
fight or they have a baby panther and
like there are lots and lots of
different animals in the animal kingdom
that just have zero trust when they see
another of their kind they try to kill
them whereas human beings we very
trusting and as a result we have an
amazing Society right we're able to
travel all over the planet I'm able to
send you money and you're able to go buy
a thing and then mail it back to me
right that's incredible and so when we
design our systems we tend to design
them with implied trust so for instance
we used to design our networks where
someone would get onto our Network you
know we would make sure they're the
right person and they are allowed there
but then once they were on the network
they could go anywhere and do anything
and that assumed trust it assumed that
this person knows oh well I'm not a
database administrator so I shouldn't go
on the database servers when in fact it
turns out not every person is
trustworthy and so we need to not trust
any sort of input or connection or
integration to any of our systems so if
we're getting input from a user whether
it be Tanya enter something into a
search bar of your web app that you made
or there's a hidden field and someone
could have changed it there's something
in the URL parameters we got something
from an API we got something from the
database that's all input to our system
and if we could validate that it's what
we're expecting and that it's okay to
use before we make any decisions or do
anything we would avoid a lot of
vulnerabilities let me tell you say with
connecting to things and integrating
with other things so we're calling an
API are we sure this is the API we meant
to call or maybe we are the API it's
like is this front end allowed to call
us is this a friendly front end is this
another API calling us should it be
calling us or is this actually a
malicious actor if we could not trust by
default and always verify before we take
our next step so before we use that data
or we open the connection or we allow
them to touch our database or access our
database I feel like at least half of
all vulnerabilities which just disappear
overnight do any real world examples
where assume trust cost failures come to
mind so as an example just SQL injection
so you get something from the user so
let's say you're filling out the form
you seem nice but I would still validate
data from you so you put something let's
say we're logging in somewhere and so
there's the username and there's the
password let's say because we're not
doing passwordless we are not fancy and
you put into the username field a bunch
of code instead of your actual username
right so instead of putting whatever
your username would be you put in a
space or a letter or something and then
a space and then a single quote and you
add on the classic in injection code
which would be or 1al 1 space- Das so
you put the two hyphens at the end and
the SQL code you're like I don't need to
see the rest of this I don't want to be
syntactically correct just end the
statement and then it goes through and
I'm trusting so instead of using
parameterized queries and instead of
validating that data I take it I
concatenate it to my select statement
and I just add it all together and ask
the database to execute it so instead of
checking that input to see if it is just
letters and numbers like it should be
for a username because that would be not
trusting right making sure that's the
correct thing then I can catenate it
together and send it to be executed so
I'm trusting there's no code in there if
I was not trusting I'd used a
parameterized query because it takes
those parameters on the database server
whether it's nosql SQL whatever query
language you're using and it removes any
power it has and it says this can only
be treated as data and I'm just super
trusting and so I execute it directly
against my database and on top of that
if I wanted to really do you know full
trust I would do it with database owner
permissions because I'm such a trusting
person right and then bad stuff happens
and so there are many many stories of
different breaches that I'm thinking of
where there is assumed Trust or there is
some sort of assumption that
everything's going to be fine I feel
like there was that this was about a
year ago there was we called it MFA
fatigue so basically a malicious actor
kept sending multiactor authentication
challenges to the system administrator
over Christmas I believe it was the
Christmas holidays and I just kept
sending them randomly over and over and
the person was like something's broken
but guess what's closed help desk right
and so they couldn't say hey could you
turn this off and So eventually after
hours and hours and even days of
constantly receiving alerts the person
just put yes and then the moous actor
was in and this was part frustration but
part also just I'm sure it'll be fine I
can trust my systems to protect us I'm
sure this is just broken I just need
this alert to stop and I mean what would
I have done if I had received literally
the 200th Alert in a row over Christmas
day I mean probably turn off my phone
right but I feel like oh my gosh almost
every single hack if you look at it a
lot of times there's an implied trust or
there's trust where there shouldn't have
been like every single fishing attack
that's ever happened it's a person who's
being tricked into clicking a link or
opening something that they should not
and it's because they trust that it is
okay okay cuz they're looking at it and
they're like how could someone possibly
know this much information about me of
course I should click this link it's
unfortunate because it plays on part of
what makes human beings wonderful and
makes us so successful and US constantly
trying to train users to be less
trusting I feel is not a winning battle
I feel like we need to have technical
controls for this rather than just
training as a person who sells training
what is the CIA Triad and how does it
help in defining secure
systems oh so classic so CIA stands for
confidentiality integrity and
availability and it is our charge so the
information security or it security team
and that includes the ABC nerds like me
it is our charge to protect the
confidentiality the integrity and the
availability of the systems and the data
that are under our care and generally a
lot of companies availability is the
most important one so are our systems up
so if you sell something online you want
that page up right if you have a store
you want the store to be open
availability tends to be number one for
a lot of businesses but when it comes to
for instance healthc care Integrity is
pretty darn important as well because if
we gave the wrong amount of medicine if
we operated on the wrong organ if we
operated on the wrong person that would
be catastrophically awful when we think
of a person with Integrity it's like is
this person trustworthy is this value is
this data is the system trustworthy and
then confidentiality is is it a secret
have we kept the secrets we are charged
with keeping and confidentiality is
still important don't get me wrong but
it tends to often be the least important
when it comes to businesses like
compared to for instance a governmental
agency that is keeping State Secrets or
for instance the tax office doesn't want
everyone to know everyone else's
financial data that's where
confidentiality would really come into
play we'll move on to the next phase
which is focus on the secure software
development life cycle and we'll get
started with the basics so what is
secure software development life cycle
and how does it differ from traditional
sdlc fantastic question about my
favorite
thing so the system development life
cycle is the methodology that you follow
to build software if you are not
following one then you will not
necessarily have great software at the
end and you probably won't have adequate
documentation you won't be sure that you
are going to create a good piece of
software each time and so a secure
system development like cycle is taking
whatever methodology the people use
where you work so let's say they're
doing devops they're doing agile they're
doing waterfall and you as the security
person you add security steps ideally to
every phase of the system development
life cycle in my opinion and I'm super
biased as a person who's obsessed with
securing software and that is my job and
career I think every single phase needs
at least one Security Act activity and
so as an example so whether you're doing
devops or agile or waterfall you still
at some point have a list of
requirements right and so I would want
there to be security requirements for
instance you know there's going to be a
pentest before we go to prod let's say
or there's going to be a secure code
review at this point in the project
we're going to have a threat model at
this time we're going to use these
security tools and our IDE to check our
code we're going to follow our secure
coding guideline or standard as it may
be you know let's say you're building a
web app with a beautiful front end
that's in a very nice JavaScript
framework and then you have a whole
bunch of backend apis and some of those
apis call a couple of serverless apps
and then there's a database and then it
also connects over to a sister company
that you have over to one of their apis
and sends data three times a day so you
would want to have in your requirements
these are the things you have to do to
secure the API these are the things for
the front end these are the rules for
connecting to a third party API this is
the API Gateway we use the serverless
app should follow this we use this type
of serverless app etc etc so really
getting kind of specific on what you
want to see I said kind of not kind of
getting specific on what you want to see
and then up next next would be design
and so if you're doing agile you might
be designing the main part of the app
first and then you might be designing
additional beautiful amazing features
that go on after but during your design
phase perhaps you do a threat model on
the main part of the app and then
whether or not you have time to threat
model the other things perhaps you do a
whiteboarding session that's one of my
favorite things so I combine the threat
modeling and the whiteboarding so thre
threat modeling is I'm friends with Adam
Shack who's very very famous for threat
modeling and I know this annoys him so
Adam if you're listening I apologize but
I like to think of it as evil
brainstorming so basically you get
together and you talk about this is what
we're doing and what could go wrong and
you brainstorm all the different threats
that there could be to your app and you
basically make a list of all the threats
and then you think about okay so which
ones of these are we actually worried
about
because for instance an asteroid could
hit planet Earth and take down your data
center but I don't feel any design
considerations I make in my app can help
with that so I'm going to leave that
risk off and just accept that risk
versus a definite threat could be could
someone do a replay attack against this
app like do we have defenses against
that and because it's transferring money
from one gift card to another gift card
we want to make sure that someone can't
Replay that transaction and then you
know if we don't have a double check to
make sure that there's money on the
other gift card if we allow it to just
run the transaction again without a
double check this could be a problem
right so that's a threat and then of
course you come up with defenses for the
threats that you find disconcerting and
so I like combining the evil
brainstorming session with a great big
huge whiteboard and you just draw out
the design and I just ask a ton of
questions and ask them to tell me about
their app and I just keep drawing and
drawing and I'm not an artist you do not
need to be an artist but I find that so
many things come out in that
conversation and sometimes the
developers discover issues that aren't
security issues but just issues with the
design it's like oh wait you thought it
was going to work like that oh no this
is what I envisioned and so talking all
the things out can really help and
documenting I could go on like I could
give examples for every single phase but
I feel like I've talked a lot no I think
it's very good so at a very high level
secure as DLC is incorporating security
into each of the development life cycles
and what we'll do is we'll double click
into each of those phases we'll start
with requirements and then you know go
into a bit more details into each of
those phase so for requirements how can
teams effectively Define security
requirements alongside functional
requirements you're really good at this
I mean that's why you're a podcast host
thanks I feel like development teams
shouldn't have to bear the Brent of this
entire responsibility themselves I feel
that security teams should be providing
a list of default requirements for each
Project based on technology and based on
policy and I'm going to explain both of
those and then they should meet with the
team to talk about specific requirements
so by default every API just needs
certain things it just does every web
app frontend needs certain things every
serverless app needs certain things iot
Etc and so ideally the way I used to
word it when I was doing appac full-time
instead of speaking and teaching about
appac full-time is I would say okay so
we have your requirements basket what
technologies are you using and I'm like
oh you're using Java great so I'm going
to want you to follow the Java secure
coding guideline so as a thing that's in
your basket now of requirements oh
you're building a web app is it a
monolith is it a microservice
architecture etc etc and I just keep
asking questions and I just keep putting
things in their mythical basket and what
I'm doing is planning to add it to the
requirements document and then we would
talk about you know what do your app do
like what is it going to do and so for
instance is it going to handle some
Health Data because guess what we have a
policy
and there is a law in many countries
that Health Data must be accessed and
protected in certain ways right are you
going to touch credit cards okay so now
we have to do PCI compliance Etc so
those would be policies Andor
legislation so you might have a policy
that states you know everyone follows
the secure coding guideline or brand new
web apps have a pentest or whatever
other rules that you might have and so
you would add all of those as well and
then as a security nerd I would want to
read over any functional requirements
that exist and see if any of them have a
partnered security requirement if that
makes sense so sometimes there are
functional requirements that just make
it clear to me that there's a security
control needed so functional
requirements are usually things that the
business has asked for the product owner
has asked for and this is kind of
similar to threat modeling because
you're looking at so this is what they
want and this is the mission or the main
purpose that this system is being built
and it's like how can I help you protect
that mission and make sure you succeed
and so that needs to be more of a
conversation and then ideally you give
them this list and it's not a thousand
years long right it needs to be a
realistic list I also usually try to
classify the app of how sensitive it is
at this point right so is this app
Mission critical to our business or our
organization does it hold extremely
sensitive data because then it might be
a high-risk app Andor project whereas it
might not be it might be medium or low
risk so there's more or less security
requirements as a result got it we're
going to move into the design phase and
you've already talked a lot about threat
modeling but I'd like to take a step
back and help explain to our listeners
what is threat modeling so the idea of
threat modeling is to
identify design
flaws within your system by talking
about threats that could take advantage
of flaws so it's if you just met up and
you're like hey what flaws could there
be in this system generally the people
that designed it don't think there are
any right because otherwise they
wouldn't have made it that way mhm and
saying oh are there any flaws here it
sounds weird but that's very difficult
but if instead you say if you were going
to hack your app how would you go about
it or to the product owner what keeps
you up at night what are you worried
about what would be the worst thing that
could happen with this system and they
might say so let's say it's a system
that gives medication it's like it gives
the wrong medication or a dose of the
medication that's wrong and it hurts a
patient that's the worst thing in the
world that could happen right and so
then you immediately start making that
can never happen versus if you're like
well what could be flaws in the system
that's a harder question if that makes
sense so there are different
methodologies for threat modeling I use
striped which is based off the stride
it's a very popular methodology where
each letter stands for something it's an
acronym to help guide you in questions
to uncover threats and so stride is
spoofing tampering
well I could go through the whole thing
but basically each one of the things the
ideas you want to figure out can someone
Elevate privileges you know is there an
Integrity problem here Etc and I changed
it to striped with a p for privacy
because although quite often security
folks aren't in charge of privacy it's
really easy to add privacy in at this
phase and make sure it's covered
properly as opposed to making privacy
engineering an entirely separate topic
and most organizations aren't big enough
to have a privacy department and to be
quite blun I really care about my users
privacy and my privacy and my loved ones
privacy so I saw a really smart lady
named Kim wz talk about this at a
conference ever since then it's just
okay so would this affect the privacy of
our users would this protect the privacy
of our staff because sometimes the users
are your staff right my teammates matter
to me I'm sure matter to you and so you
walk through each one of these letters
and each part of your system if you
could bring a data flow diagram that
would be awesome and an architecture
diagram or a design diagram but an
architecture diagram is great each
different parts like so this part talks
to this part right okay so repudiation
which is a security word but basically
how can we make sure are we keeping
track of who did this is there a way
this person could deny that it was them
could someone else go do this
transactions that would be spoofing
could someone else do a transaction and
pretend it's me and charge my account
right like what could happen here that
could go wrong what are you worried
about and I feel like having this
discussion including so generally you
invite a security representative you
invite a product representative so the
product owner business rep whoever and
then at least one technical person I
feel like you really open people's eyes
when you have a threat modeling
conversation and I find that those
developers they design differently after
a threat modeling conversation
especially if you threat model the
mission of your organization if that
makes sense so if you start with that
conversation as training they look at
everything differently from then on so
for instance when I worked at elections
Canada we threat modeled the election
and it's like what's the worst thing
that could go wrong and for every
democracy there are two things that
they're very worried about and one is
voter suppression that is people
tricking people into not voting or
scaring them or preventing them from
voting when they legitimately should be
able to vote and the other is that the
public do not fully believe the results
because that is a nightmare it's a
nightmare for your country it's a
nightmare for the elections Department
Etc and so how many different ways can
we assure that neither of those ever
happen and so then every single system
from then on you have that those two
threats in mind no matter what the
system is that you're modeling if that
makes sense and so threat modeling is
educational but I'm just going to be a
little biased here it's so fun it's
really a fascinating activity I really
enjoy it and just to be clear developers
if you're listening and you go to your
first one and you're not good at it
that's okay because this is a muscle and
it is your evil muscle
and you have spent your whole career
figuring out how to make things work and
how to satisfy customers needs and solve
amazing complex problems but now you
need to take off your developer hat as
my mentor used to say to me and put on
your malicious actor evil hat and think
about how you could undo all the
greatness that you did which is really
hard at first but once you do a few rap
models it'll be hilarious like you'll be
at the movie theater and you're like
this security is pathetic I could so see
12 movies for free if I wanted to it
sounds funny but like a lot of security
especially physical security really
isn't that good it keeps out the honest
people and when you start doing threat
modeling you start seeing flaws in
systems everywhere and you design better
systems like flat out you just do right
moving on to the coding phase what are
the most common secure coding guidelines
developers should follow so I written
some books and in my first book I had
the most basic secure coding guideline
ever it's like anyone ever can start
with this for web apps and it's like
when you go on a roller coaster when
you're little and you have to be a
certain height or you're not allowed on
it's like if you want to put an app on
the internet you must do these 17 things
or you're just not good enough and the
first one is you need to validate and
then San
or Escape all input so you validate that
it is what you're expecting to see so
you validate the size and the type and
the range so let's say it's a date of
birth so guess what date of birth better
be in the past and it probably shouldn't
be more than 150 years ago and it should
probably be an actual date that someone
submits right and it should be in the
date format that you're expecting and if
it's all those things you've validated
it and it's good and it's safe to use
but let's say it's a search term well
that's a lot more complicated right
imagine stack Overflow they have to
accept code it's so hard right so you
would validate let's say that it's no
longer than 150 characters maybe that's
how long you're allowing people to do
and then you want to make sure probably
needs to be one or more characters in a
search term probably more than one but
let's say it's one so you validate that
but then you're like gosh I have to
accept a lot of really dangerous
characters so I'm going to go through
and you can either sanitize them and
that means taking out the scary
characters and replacing them with
something else or just even removing
them completely depending upon what
you're doing or you escape them and so
you generally just add a backslash in
front of any bad characters and so
that's number one just validating every
single input to your app and making sure
that it is reasonable to use and then
sanitizing or sking any special
characters you must accept but if it
does not validate you reject you do not
fix it you're like I'm sorry no one is
500 years old science is not that good
yet please try again you just reject it
bad input we're expecting a date range
between this and this please try again
here's the format we're looking for
please try again the second thing would
be at all output to the screen for web
types of applications must be encoded
and depending upon you know if you're a
bit of a cowboy and you're doing inline
JavaScript all throughout your HTML then
you might have to do a whole bunch of
different types of encoding you might
have to Nest it quite a bit but ideally
we're not doing that because life is
easier then if you output encode
everything that goes to the screen then
we've turned off the possibility of cros
a scripting between those to well we've
generally prevented cros a scripting
there's more protections for that
the third one would be always using
parameterized queries and never ever
ever doing inline or dynamic SQL that is
a recipe for injection and same with no
SQL so if you're using mongodb it's
still very injectable so no matter what
the type of database is that you're
using using whatever version of their
parameterized queries so like prepared
statements or procedures there's so many
different names for them but database
servers are very powerful and they will
take away all of its superpowers if use
parameterized queries definitely feel
developers should use security headers
so HTTP headers that instruct the
browser to perform certain security
functions for you so content security
policy header is the most powerful
amazing one especially for stopping
crossy scripting but I want us to use
all of them that make sense right like
almost all of them are worth using I
created a security header cheat sheet
that you can get from my website so if
you go to newsletter. shehacks
purple.car Tab and I'm adding more
resources there all the time but
basically there's a cheat sheet that you
can get that it tells you what every
single header does and when you need to
use it and spoiler alert most of them
are like you have
to and then you could just copy and
paste the configuration so content
security policy header there's some work
there but most of them there's almost no
work like hsts or HTTP strict Transport
Security the long form it just makes
sure that if someone tries to connect
you with HTTP it just redirects them to
https and it never ever ever allows
anyone to connect un encrypted there's
no need for that anymore right like the
internet is lightning fast we've
discovered many ways that people can
abuse
HTTP and so it just makes sure that
there's never a mistake right and it's
so effortless it's one line of code to
just make absolute sure I will talk
about security headers all day if you
allow it I'll make sure that we add a
link to the cheat sheet in our show
notes but to summarize it to make sure
that I've got everything that you
mentioned you know and the top four in
your mind from a secure coding
guidelines would be to ensure that we
validate an escape the inputs we encode
the outputs we use parameterized queries
and we use security headers absolutely
okay great how does code review change
when we adopt secure coding practices
should a security professional be part
of the code review process ideally
because there's way fewer security
people than there are software
developers ideally you've trained your
software developers that are doing the
code review on secure code review so
essentially you have some sort of secure
coding guideline or you give them some
sort of guidance and it's like these are
the things that we want you to look for
when you're reviewing code so if you
give them secure coding training and I
actually have a free secure coding
course on the internet and if we could
link to that that might be helpful and
it covers the 17 things you add a link
to that awesome basically if you could
give them a secure coding course and say
when you review code look for these
things and even better if you could give
them a checklist and I'm huge on
checklists and so all my courses have
checklists because that's how I like to
work and so if you can give them a
checklist of when they're reviewing code
then they know what to look for and so
as an example you know whenever there's
input to a system it's like you need to
check that there's input validation and
either escaping or sanitizing and you
need to make sure apps abute sure that
it happens before you do anything with
that input so we don't want to take the
input make our query to the database and
then validate it after we must do it
before we do anything else with it and
so going through and explaining to the
people reviewing code these are the
things we want you to look for and this
is what it looks like when it's good and
this is what it looks like when it's bad
because if you think about it if they
don't know what it looks like when it's
bad it be easy to miss and so for
security controls bad looks like missing
in the wrong place or incorrectly
implemented so missing is the most
common where someone has not implemented
let's say an anti-c surf token they just
haven't done it at all or they've
implemented it but in this case
incorrectly so I've seen an anti-c serf
token being passed manually when for
instance net does it for you so there's
just no need for you to also pass one
you need to validate it but you don't
have to manually create one and pass it
it does it for you which is awesome good
job.net a bunch of them do it and a
bunch of them don't right and so if you
make sure you're like this is what it
looks like in net when this happens and
this is where you should validate this
sorry to cut you T but what's an anti-
ceser of token yes I am so sorry so Cerf
stands for cross-site request forgery
and when we perform a transaction on the
internet we want to also pass a token
back and forth and it sounds weird but
it can totally be in clear text it
doesn't even matter it's just a random
value and we pass it back and forth and
when we do the final transaction we
check that the anti-c serve token is
still correct that they're giving us the
right token and we do this because
because of fishing so I don't know about
you but I'm currently logged into Amazon
and probably a ton of other sites that I
use regularly and I've clicked the
remember me and all of that because I
trust my own computer and my home
network but if I clicked on a fishing
link that was to buy a great big TV and
send it to you instead of me right so I
click on This fishing link that you
you've become evil you by the way in
this scenario and so you send me an
email I'm having a bad day I don't think
and I click on this link when it goes to
amazon.com Amazon's like Hey where's
your anti-c surf token and you aren't
going to have it as the fishing person
right because it's stuck in my browser
going back and forth and then it can
tell this is a Seas surf attack and the
transaction does not go through and
whereas on my computer where I'm logged
in I have the ATC surf token and if for
whatever reason like you know it's
needed to refresh it's expired or
whatever it just says hey is this
actually Tanya and I reauthenticate and
then it lets me buy my theoretical giant
television so there are several
Frameworks that will do that for you and
several that do not and so first of all
informing everyone yeah it does this for
you so don't worry about it chill out
you're all good you don't need to review
for that or it does do it but you need
to do the final check on on the back end
so for instance like there's a lot of
really cool JavaScript front ends that
will create one and pass it to you but
if you're not validating it on the other
end there's no protection right so
telling the people doing the code review
these things and that you know this is
where this would happen this is what
this would look like that's what I find
is best so secure coding training
essentially that includes so the way I
teach I'm always like so we talk about a
thing and I give a lot of examples and
we look at some like this intact but
then I'm like here's some code and this
code is bad and I want you all to tell
me exactly why it's bad and usually it's
missing something or it's in the wrong
place or I've done a terrible job or
whatever right and then I'll improve it
I'm like okay so this code's better why
is it better than what we saw and then
sometimes I'm like this codee's the best
code and usually I've Incorporated like
multiple things that we've learned at
this point into it and I'm like what's
good here am I missing anything like why
is this code the best of the three codes
right and doing that review together and
talking about it it sounds weird but
like we'll go through and we'll
highlight things and we're looking at
but I'm like but why I'm super annoying
with the why question because I they
know I know but I want to know that they
know and so having a discussion so even
if you're in the class and you didn't
know why when you hear your colleague
like hit that light bulb and they're
like oh because we took it it and then
we used it and then we validated it oh
crap that's what we did the wrong spot
yeah we have the right Security Control
in the wrong location and then you know
we go through and of course at the end
it's in the right location right and so
I feel like walking through and
discussing code review can really help
and also using to be quite BLT using
codeview tools you could use so conflict
of interest alert I work at a company
that sells a static analysis tool but
all stack analysis tools are very
helpful and so you can use a stack
analysis tool to help you look for
implementation issues like where you've
incorrectly implemented a security
control it will also help you see a lot
of places that you've missed a security
control and so most of them or at least
half will allow you to write your own
rules that you can put into the tool and
so they're usually called custom rules
some marketing teams are calling them
secure guard
rails but basically if you have a secure
coding guideline and the stack analysis
tool isn't picking up all the things you
want it to pick up you can write your
own rules to pick up the things that you
need it to do so often the security team
does this but the devs can do this too
right because they're just writing
patterns and devs are amazing at
patterns and so basically you can do
this to enforce anything in your coding
guideline so that could mean like we all
use camel case no one uses snake case it
could mean we name our variables this
way or we all use this security header
and if we're not using it I want it to
flag it and so you can write rules and
kind of customize things for yourselves
especially if you are using a language
that doesn't have a great rule set so
like elixir or something where maybe
your SAS provider only has 10 things it
checks but you know there's way more
that you want it to check or C and C++ a
lot of SAS tools aren't really strong in
that area and so you could write your
own usually with the help of the
security team but there are developers
that are like get out of my way I've got
this so it depends but I find manual
code review partnered with automated or
basically static analysis you'll get the
absolute best results definitely well
the SAS tool allows us to do nicely move
on to the next phase which is around
testing so what are the key types of
security testing that should be included
in sslc depending upon what your system
does performance and stress testing
which are not quite the same but often
done by the same person at the same time
just making sure that you can handle a
huge load and that you perform well
under heavy loads because availability
is really important to the security team
and well everyone it's important to
everyone and although technically
usually people don't consider that
security test I consider it a priority
for the security team depending upon
what the system does I would say doing
some sort of final static analysis check
making sure that there's no obvious
security bugs I would say doing I scan
my codes for secrets so a secret would
be something that a computer uses to
authenticate to another computer so an
API key a hash a certificate a password
a connection string there's many many
types of Secrets but it's computer to
computer instead of human to computer
and so I scan my code for Secrets
because I don't believe Secrets should
be in code I believe they should be in a
secret management tool or another place
that's safe so some Frameworks offer you
basically a Secret store a place that is
safe where you can put it and you access
it programmatically and but most of them
don't and so a secret management tool
can help with that so I scan for Secrets
I don't want to give my secrets away if
I could do lenting for code quality so I
don't consider a linter technically a
security tool however if you are
ensuring you have good code quality it's
just better you're building a better
more reliable application and that
generally means also better security so
I am very Pro linter and then Dynamic an
analysis and so there are several
different types of dynamic analysis
tools so Dynamic analysis means your app
or your API or your server lless or
whatever is running so it can be on a
Dev server or a test server somewhere
but it's running and these tools
interact with your app live and they can
make a mess so usually the security team
runs those an example would be like burp
sweet or zap there's also tools that are
specific for apis because a lot of the
super automated dast Dynamic scanning
Dynamic application security testing
tools dast a lot of them really suck
with apis like they're good with a big
monolithic web app but when it comes to
like a microservice architecture they
get really lost or with a spa single
page web app they're just they're
terrible so you would want to use
something more specific for an apepi and
they're I don't know of a good Dynamic
tool for Spas yet so basically then I
would depending upon the system and the
budget if you can have a penetration
test done so that's where a security
expert comes and they interact with your
application Live they usually use
something like burp s or zap or both
they usually use a whole bunch of other
tools and they will manually test your
app they'll have scripts run they'll try
to Brute Force things they'll Buzz every
input so fuzzing is really important
fuzzing is where you test every sing
Single part of the input validation of
every single field and I remember the
first time I saw fuzzer run it put the
letter A into the field and I'm like
okay this is pretty boring and then it
put 50 of the letter A I'm like okay and
then 500 and then 5,000 of the letter a
and it goes through and tries all these
special characters and sees what it can
get and then it it tells the tester I
put these characters in and it acts
weird please go destroy this app you use
this information to eventually create an
exploit and you figure out where there's
flaws in the input validation if you are
doing proper validation with an allow
list and you're doing it on the server
side and like you won't the fuzzer won't
get anywhere but almost everyone uses a
block list even though like almost
everyone that has errors uses a block
list or they're doing it in the front
end JavaScript instead of doing it on
the back end like they're supposed to
they made a mistake they've put it in
the wrong place then the fuzzer will
show you your errors it's really a
powerful tool but it can make a gigantic
mess so generally the security team runs
Dynamic tools including fuzzers if you
can so this is a weird one so it's
called testing but I wouldn't put it in
the testing phase you put it out into
production or you put it in during all
your tests and then again and production
so it's called I asked interactive
application security test testing and
that happens it's a binary that goes up
inside of your application and it does
static and dynamic analysis as your app
runs but it only works if your app is
being actively used and so if you have
it in your app just on the dev server
well I don't know about you but I don't
do s super thorough testing on the dev
server I'm kind of kicking it around and
playing with it a bit but it's not the
same as having 2,000 users on it every
day right and so you generally deploy it
during a a penetration test and QA
testing and then in production and it
tests your app from the inside out IAS
is quite
expensive like expensive and causes a
bit of latency and it is a ton of work
in order to install it installing it is
so complicated it has its own name it's
called
instrumentation so generally I I only
see iasts at Banks or really super
Mission critical system where there's a
lot of money involved I would say maybe
1% of all my clients use iast and so but
it's still really cool technology like
it's very interesting let's be clear and
so those are the types of tests that I
would like to do so manual testing and
automated testing oh and I missed one oh
my
gosh I want to secure my supply chain
and so there are two things I would do
one is use a software composition
analysis tool so SCA to check all my
dependencies see which ones have
vulnerabilities in them and then ideally
it also checks if you know I have a
dependency and it has a vulnerability
does my code call the vulnerability like
does it is it reachable from within my
app or is there no path in the code that
ever gets there and so if it's not
reachable I might fix it later if it's
really really high risk then I might fix
it quickly but generally if it's not
reachable I'm not that concerned yes
it's a time bomb in your app
theoretically but I mean if you have the
math Library are you doing every single
type of math are you doing derivatives
and calculus and geometry probably not
right and so if you're doing geometry
and it's in the I don't know calculus
area your app's not going to suddenly
need to do calculus probably and so if
it's not reachable from with your code
it's not usually exploitable and then I
just leave it but the other thing for
securing your supply chain ideally part
of the requirements phase of your
project there's a checklist for your
supply chain so these are the security
settings that we want for rcii these are
security settings that we have for any
sandbox area these are the security
settings or the rules for releasing code
in the CI like here are the people that
have approvals here are the people that
are notified Etc even like people forget
but it took you a while to set up your
IDE just right backing that up or or
writing down even just like these are
the plugins I have and that I'd want to
use if my laptop got ransomware and I
had to set everything up again like
these are the things that I use just
knowing that and being able to set
everything up again very quickly is
really important so but you would
probably just need to do that once for
your supply chain for the project just
you know make sure that you're following
all the policies or the rules or the
checklist whatever it is that your
organization does but for software
composition analysis like I would run it
every time I check my code in just in
case I've you know upgraded a dependency
unfortunately to something that's not
secure or a new vulnerability has been
found since the last time I checked in
I'm like oh this is not very good I
should do something that's quite an
exhaustive list you've covered manual
and dynamic and automated test you've
covered performance test Secrets L using
of Lent
youve covered sast Das
I and supply chain securing the supply
chain as well I've done a lot of
security testing in my
life I do have a ton of questions you
know on each of them but we won't be
able to cover all of that but in terms
of tools which actually run on
production say IST does that not impact
the performance of the system and don't
users see degradation when you're
running the test for I asked there is
latency there absolutely is and do users
see it I think that if you have a system
that needs so the latency of course
according to the people that make I asks
is very small I would say that's
something you really need to validate
for yourself so all of these systems or
all the security testing tools anyway
you can turn off a bunch of tests if you
want to so they go faster all of them
are designed that way knowing devs want
to move fast and so the security team
wants you to be able to move fast too or
I would hope any decent security team
knows that's a priority and because it's
the developer priority it should be
their priority too and so with I asked
or anything that you wanted to test in
production quite often you can just
remove a lot of tests that you don't
think are that important if it's going
too slow I also often suggest testing in
off hours if that's a possibility so I
used to work for the Canadian government
and although Canada has five time zones
CU we're ginormous there's still many
hours per day where theoretically no one
or almost no one's at work right and so
we would schedule as many things as
possible to run during that time but if
you are for instance running an online
Marketplace it needs to be open all the
time probably right and so then that's a
lot more difficult but yes you're right
it totally can cause latency and that's
one of the reasons that I asked is not
as popular and it's used so rarely I
would say though no matter what if you
are going to have you know a production
system that has any importance to you
I'd want to have monitoring and logging
turned on and although that does cause a
small amount of latency I want to know
that my app is down before anyone else
knows I don't want my customer to call
me and tell me it's down I want it to
already be back up before they get
through on the phone yeah makes a lot of
sense also can you expand on any
security considerations developers or
the team should think about post Gove in
terms of Maintenance and continuous
Improvement yes this is a weird one
because when I go to do application
security at different places I like to
spend 50% of my time on apps that are
already in prod which I call Legacy
which I do not mean to offend just to be
clear like I know if your app came out 6
months ago you don't feel its Legacy but
I have to have a name for it and so
whatever you want to call that let's say
I'm calling it the same thing as you and
a lot of workplaces are like no just
focus on the new apps but most
organizations unless they're a startup
have more apps in prod than they're
currently developing right and older
applications we knew less about security
when they were developed and unless
they've had a big update or refactor
rewrite or a lot of security attention
they're often not in a great state and
so I try to have half my time on those
and so I try to set up automated testing
on all of them so an easy thing you can
do is on your code repository set it you
know get a static analysis tool a secret
scanner a software composition analysis
tool and set them to scan every Sunday
or whatever day works for you and they
can't hurt anything because they're
static so they just need read only
access to the code and then just go
check out the reports every Monday right
like that would be one thing that you
could do and we do this because the
tools get updated with new types of
tests so the tools are learning we do
this because software ages very poorly
the longer it is out in production the
longer there is a chance for a malicious
actor to figure out something wrong with
it right you could set up Dynamic
testing so pen testers always say it
must be production or you don't really
know if the test isn't perfectly
accurate if it's not production but I
gently disagree I'd rather have a
pre-prod or staging environment that is
a perfect mirror to production except
for there's not as much power behind it
right so the performance isn't as good
because it's staging which is fine but
if every other thing matches which I
feel it should then you can do a
fantastic test there and so running
Dynamic tests
there maybe once a month or more if you
have the Cycles you can automate them to
run regularly with Dynamic testing
there's API tools that can just run all
the time and it just checks the requests
and responses to the apis and tells you
if it sees something disconcerting so I
would like to have a lot of automated
security testing happening but on top of
that I need logging turned on and I need
I talk a little bit I would say at
length in both my books about logging
because I've had to do incident response
to security incidents at a lot of places
that I've worked and if I get there and
there's no logs or there's really not
very good logs there's no evidence for
me to press charges there's no evidence
for me to figure out what happened
there's no evidence for me to figure out
how to prevent this from happening again
just as when you're trying to
troubleshoot something if there's no
logs you're like how am I supposed to
troubleshoot this it's very similar
except for I can't even debug it right
because it happened in the past so it's
not like I can put a ton of break points
in the code and run it and see what
happened if there's no logs I'm
literally completely unable to
investigate and so logging is really
important so if we have monitoring
turned on we find out if our system
hopefully we find out if we're being
attacked we find out if our system's
down we find out if our system's
struggling with logging we can go and
investigate see what's happened and some
sometimes it's just a coding problem
right it's a regular bug it's not a
security attack that's fine I still want
to know I still want us to be able to
fix it and have visibility there on top
of that on all of those is are some
newer tools called observability tools
and they help us investigate and they
are super Nifty observability focus on
like let's detect what's happening right
now where logs are what happened in the
past right and observability focuses on
so like I'm detecting an incident
happening right an attack is happening
right now so that you can take action
right now if you have a cloud provider
and your apps are in the cloud you can
also have the cloud detect certain
things um I believe Azure calls it
threat protection and you can create a
logic app and with that then call a
serverless app or inst the cloud to take
certain actions this is more advanced
and this is something generally the
security team would do but you know if
you detect something that looks like
injection you know send an email or
phone the security team immediately and
block that IP address permanently or you
know this looks like a Dos attack or
maybe instead of a Dos let's say a Dos
so a denial of service attack rather
than a distributed denial of service
attack which is much more difficult to
respond to you know we're seeing this
one IP with a ton of traffic so we're
just going to block it right away you
know no legitimate customer is going to
behave that way so we feel confident
just automatically attacking it and
notifying the security team those are
things generally the security team would
set up for you but ideally they're going
to talk to the developers about them
because they don't want to break stuff I
really don't want to be the security
team that is the threat to availability
right that's bad that's a bad look and
so ideally they're going to ask advice
and guidance from the developers and
work with them on these things so
logging monitoring if you can have your
app send alerts as well so again I I
talk about this a lot so when you get to
for instance the global exception
Handler this means all your tries and
catches have failed right everything has
gone wrong if you call the global
exception Handler maybe there should be
an alert that goes to the dev team that
says hey the global exception Handler
got called maybe you need to figure out
what went wrong here and look into this
or maybe someone has tried to log in 10
times in under one second that seems
very wrong to you and maybe an alert
should be set and this is again
something the security team would work
on with you of when you would want to
trigger an alert and where this alert
goes like is the alert an email is the
alert a phone call cuz I didn't know the
cloud can phone you I know because when
I worked at my Microsoft Azure phoned my
boss to tell on me that I checked a
secret into production however I checked
a pretend secret into production so I
could make an a demo of what you're not
supposed to do okay but Azure then
reacted and phoned my boss and my boss
was like whoa did you know azer can make
phone calls I did not he's like also
what the heck are you doing and I
explained and then we made fun of aure
but anyway I feel like the security team
would work with you on these things and
so what does an alert look like does an
alert go to your security information
and event management system your sim if
so what format does that look like Does
the Sock the security Operation Center
know what this alert means and know what
to do so I feel like this is different
for each organization but I like it when
an app can call for help when it needs
it yep makes sense I think we have
covered or double clicked into each of
the pH Within sdlc
and see what specific security measures
should be considered in each of those
phases are there metrics or kpis key
performance indicators that teams can
track to ensure security is integrated
effectively how do they measure success
oh I love this question I'm a big fan of
metrics and Gathering data and then
using data to improve and so generally
when I run an appac program or I'm part
of an appsec program we choose a
specific security posture that we want
to be at and different apps have
different risks and therefore need
different postures and by posture I mean
how secure it is how tough and rugged it
is how many tests we've done how many
layers of protection we've used so for
instance I did counter terrorism at one
point in my career and we did every
single thing you can think of and when I
was the ciso for the election in Canada
we did every single thing you can think
of at least twice like literally twice
but I've also written apps that don't
need very much of anything and the super
famous example I use is I used to run
this lunch and learn program I ran like
a community of practice for my Dev team
for many years and it got very popular
and eventually I ran it and we streamed
it across the Canadian government to all
like 70,000 software developers and we
just had like this little web app with
the schedule that is very low priority
if it goes down it is not important the
data inside it's not important and the
system was not connected to other
systems it was just a hardcoded database
with what I put into it no one else
accessed it and it was just select
statements right and so the risk I don't
need to do a bunch of security testing
on this this is fine right and it was
just within my governmental department
so only 2,000 people could see it etc
etc like there was just the risk is so
low right so I would say that I create
goals for my program and certain
security postures for each system and
then I measure myself against those so
my first goal every time I start
somewhere is I want to do an inventory
of all my web apps and apis and
serverless apps and I need to know where
the code is where links are in every
environment what team that this belongs
to and how to contact them a brief
description of what it does its
sensitivity rating so usually I have one
to three year one to four so like this
is a four I need to do the works this is
a one I don't have to do very much and
then any documentation just links to
documentation if I can figure out how it
fits into the larger architecture that's
even nicer but just doing an inventory
thing and then I want to be able to run
whatever scanners I have on 100% of
those apps and then look to see which
ones are in a bad State and then I
prioritize them and I figure out what
state I I want them to be in and that is
the start and then I take all of those
results and I shove them into Excel
because Excel is the best security tool
ever paid Excel and
browsers and I mash all that data up and
I figure out what our top security
concerns are like mistakes we keep
repeating and I educate on those
immediately and I tell all the devs I'm
really worried about those two or three
or four things and I start to try to get
action on those big things immediately
and if I I do that for 90 days then I re
measure everything so yes I did complete
the inventory or I'm like half done or
whatever I have rated the apps or I have
not I have gotten especially when you
rescan three months later you know
instances of these things that I've been
educating on went down or they're the
same or it's worse in which case I'm a
total failure usually they go way down
and then I can see okay so this is where
I'm at this is how much traction I can
get with the developer teams right away
this is how close I am to security
posture I feel is responsible and
reasonable for our organization and then
I set better goals like that's just my
crash first 90 days when I start
somewhere I came to that over many years
but if you already have a security
program your goals might be you know all
the devs hate our stack analysis tool so
this happened to me I went somewhere and
we'd signed a three-year contract with a
big company and all the devs had
disabled it everywhere they hated it and
they're very they'd had bad experiences
with it so it didn't matter if I could
implement it in a new way that was nicer
they were just like we hate it no so I
ripped it all out and I did Proof of
concepts with a bunch of other ones and
we found one that they liked and I
rolled it out everywhere and that was my
project for 90 days and just how well am
I doing against this project and Dev
feedback was part of my rating of myself
and my project like are they satisfied
with this new tool are they using it so
like when I started seeing them use it
without me I was just like oh my gosh oh
my gosh oh my gosh it's working and so I
feel your security team needs to set
goals and then measure against those
goals as opposed to oh last quarter we
had 200,000 vulnerabilities and we now
we have
199,000 vulnerabilities I feel like are
those vulnerabilities a concern just
because some automated system picked it
up it doesn't actually mean that it
causes business risk right I feel like a
lot of companies I met with a company a
few weeks ago and they're like well how
many bugs per app is reasonable like are
they even really bugs they're like we
don't have time to look at that I'm like
well then we have a problem if you're
like I don't have time to even look at
that you want a Dev to take time to fix
[Music]
it yeah excellent we've covered a lot of
ground over here but before we wrap up T
what's one piece of advice you'd give to
developers or teams looking to get
started with secure sdlc today I have
two pieces of advice and one is really
cheap if you are going to look up how to
do something online this is just general
advice look up how to do it securely
because whatever is rated the top on any
website ever is the least secure way to
do it it's unfortunate but it's
extraordinarily common if something is
at the top of the stack Overflow
whatever I love stack overflow but it's
often all the security features have
been turned off in order to make it work
in every instance so please look at the
most secure way so now that I've gotten
that advice out of the way that I really
want people to know I would say so I'm
quite biased but I have a a class that I
made that is free that's online that we
can link to that will teach you how to
build your own secure system development
life cycle and it's completely free
there's no upsell the idea is that I got
some to host all my courses for free as
part of the acquisition deal because
that's what I wanted was for them to be
free because I want people to have more
secure sdlcs and so it's called
application security foundations and it
will teach you about every single step
that you can do and then it helps you
build your own program and I was
teaching that like live to companies and
helping them build their programs as
like Consulting gigs and then I was like
how can I make this so everyone can do
it themselves like how can I teach a
person to fish and so it starts off with
telling you all the different activities
that exist all the different types of
tools that exist all the different parts
of your program that you could have and
then as you learn each one it's like so
how would you apply this where you work
and what would make sense for your org
and then you learn about policies so
what policies could support these things
what you know guidance could we give how
could we teach developers about this how
etc etc how can we scale this program in
the most effective way and it builds and
builds on your program over the three
courses and every single course is free
in the academy there's no charges and
the idea is that at the end you have
this nine-page plan to launch a full
absc program or to improve upon the
program that you have and I did that
because I really want everyone to build
better software I just do and so you
could start by taking that class
but if you don't want to take a class
that is okay I would start with creating
a secure code guideline think about the
coding that your organization does and
start with that if you have no guidance
for developers whatsoever a coding
guideline can really help and you build
it and then you get feedback and then
you update it and then you get more
feedback and then you update it because
your first copy trust me on this is not
going to be great I know I've built some
not great ones and I worked and worked
and worked to create better and better
and once you have it and people agree
it's pretty good you want to teach it
you want to socialize it and make sure
that everyone at your organization knows
it exists they know where to find it and
ideally you've literally taught it to
them that would be the absolute best
that has been a large part of many of my
absc jobs is coming up with a guideline
and teaching it so that developers know
what we want from them and the guideline
can include like we use the SAS tool or
this is the secret scanner or what
whatever tools you expect them to use it
could just be four things to start if
that's all the traction that you think
you can get that's okay but you really
really really want to start somewhere
and that might be a good spot perfect
thank you Tanya for coming on the show
it's been a real pleasure this is bries
am manut for software engineering radio
thank you for listening thank you so
much for having
me thanks for listen listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at sc-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at
team-
radio.net this and all other episodes of
SC radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license 2 5 thanks for listening